Ashkah אשכח Ashkah Rab Yaakov bar Acha רב יעקב
בר אחא Rav Yaakov bar Acha at the top of nun zayin
amud bet נ"ז עמוד ב', Nun Zayin Amud Bet, the third word
in from the top. Ashkah אשכח Ashkah Rab Yaakov bar Acha רב
יעקב בר אחא Rav Yaakov bar Acha de-itktav be-Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav
דאיתכתב בספר אגדתא דבי רב. de-itktav be-Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav. So Rab
Yaakov bar Acha רב יעקב בר אחא Rav Yaakov bar Acha he
found in the book, the book of Aggadata אגדתא. Aggadata. It sounds
like a different kind of book than our Sefer Aggadata ספר אגדתא
Sefer Aggadata since it has halakhic material rather than aggadic material.
So maybe this was a book of halakhot הלכות halakhot sort of,
rather than aggadot אגדות. aggadot. So de-itktav be-Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav דאיתכתב
בספר אגדתא דבי רב, de-itktav be-Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav, Ben Noach neherag
be-dayan echad uve-ed echad she-lo be-haztara mipi ish velo mipi isha ve-afilo
karov בן נח נהרג בדיין אחד ובעד אחד שלא בהתראה מפי איש
ולא מפי אשה ואפילו קרוב. Ben Noach neherag be-dayan echad uve-ed echad
she-lo be-haztara mipi ish velo mipi isha ve-afilo karov.
So he has this law that a Ben Noach בן נח Ben
Noach can be killed by one judge, by one witness,
and without a warning, as long as it's a man and not
a woman doing something unusual, i.e. the judge or the witness. And
this comes in stark contrast with
the
halakha הלכה halakha for Jews, which
requires at least for capital punishment, it requires twenty-three dayanin דיינים dayanin
and two edim עדים edim and haztara התראה. haztara. The rule at
ish velo isha איש ולא אשה ish velo isha though, does remain
for both. So, they're inconsistent there. So ve-afilo karov ואפילו קרוב, ve-afilo
karov, and even... sorry... ve-afilo karov ואפילו קרוב, ve-afilo karov, and even
the other thing about a non-Jew, Noachite laws, Noach נח, Noach, laws,
the Noach high laws, the sheva mitzvot bnei Noach שבע מצוות בני
נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach is that even a karov קרוב karov
could testify. We're at the top of nun zayin
amud bet נ"ז עמוד ב'. Nun Zayin Amud Bet.
I know. Okay, great. So,
and even a relative could testify against a relative. So typically we
would say in a Jewish court if one person's brother is either
a judge or a witness, that case would not stand. We don't
allow a relative to be a part of testimony, but in the
case of a non-Jew we see that it's okay. So Rabbi Yishmael
amru רבי ישמעאל אמרו, Rabbi Yishmael amru, and they said Rabbi Yishmael
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael also is in Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav ספר
אגדתא דבי רב. Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav. Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav ספר
אגדתא דבי רב Sefer Aggadata De-bei Rav is some sort of collection
or some book of text that has things also said in the
name of Rabbi Yishmael רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in it. Af al
ha-ubarim
אף על העוברים. Af al ha-ubarim.
He says that even
somebody
who kills a fetus
can
be killed in this way. Minayan מנין? Minayan? So, how do we
know this? Amar Kra אמר קרא, Amar Kra, Ach et dimchem lenafshoteichem
edrosh אך את דמכם לנפשותיכם אדרוש. Ach et dimchem lenafshoteichem edrosh. So
they interpret edrosh אדרוש, edrosh, I will seek, afilu be-dayan echad אפילו
בדיין
אחד. afilu be-dayan echad. Just to be clear, let me actually open
the pesukim פסוקים. pesukim. These are... these are the pesukim פסוקים pesukim
from when Hashem ה' Hashem is giving mitzvot מצוות mitzvot to the
bnei Noach בני נח bnei Noach essentially, and this is where a
lot of the derashot דרשות derashot come from in terms of determining
how the law system works.
I wouldn't say it's necessarily the most compelling derasha דרשה, derasha, but
on the other hand they are all tied back to pesukim פסוקים.
pesukim. So... one second...
this is Perek Tet Pasuk He פרק ט' פסוק ה', Perek Tet
Pasuk He, Ve-ach et dimchem lenafshoteichem edrosh ואך את דמכם לנפשותיכם אדרוש.
Ve-ach et dimchem lenafshoteichem edrosh. However your blood which belongs to your
souls, I will demand. And we pick up on the singleness to
say even with one judge, that would be enough to kill a
Ben Noach בן נח. Ben Noach. Mi-yad kol chaya edroshenu מיד כל
חיה אדרשנו, Mi-yad kol chaya edroshenu, and the fact that it says
in the continuation of the pasuk פסוק pasuk says mi-yad kol chaya
edroshenu מיד כל חיה אדרשנו, mi-yad kol chaya edroshenu, and of every
beast I will demand that justice will be demanded even of a
beast. So even a beast who
we know you couldn't warn because they don't have
consciousness, and nonetheless they'd be put to death. So to man, in
this case a Ben Noach בן נח, Ben Noach, he without haztara
התראה haztara would be put to death. Edroshenu אדרשנו, Edroshenu, sorry... so
mi-yad ha-adam edroshenu מיד האדם אדרשנו. mi-yad ha-adam edroshenu.
Mi-yad ha-adam מיד
האדם,
Mi-yad ha-adam,
and then we have mi-yad ha-adam מיד האדם, mi-yad ha-adam, afilu be-ed
echad אפילו בעד אחד. afilu be-ed echad. And then mi-yad ish מיד
איש, mi-yad ish, and the pasuk פסוק pasuk also says mi-yad ish
מיד איש, mi-yad ish, mi-yad ha-adam mi-yad ish achiv מיד האדם מיד
איש אחיו, mi-yad ha-adam mi-yad ish achiv, edrosh et nefesh ha-adam אדרוש
את נפש האדם. edrosh et nefesh ha-adam. So mi-yad ish מיד איש,
mi-yad ish, that comes to teach ish velo mipi isha איש ולא
מפי אשה, ish velo mipi isha, a man and not from a
woman. So all these things, the dayan דיין dayan and the ed
עד ed who play... So מיד איש, miyad ish, that comes to
teach איש ולא מיד אשה, ish v'lo miyad isha, a man and
not a woman. So all these things they can be apply by
a man and not by a woman. אחיו, Achiv, and the fact
it says this brother means even a relative. משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו,
Mishum Rabi Yishmael amru, אף על העוברים. af al ha'ubarim. מאי טעמא
דרבי ישמעאל? Mai ta'ama d'Rabi Yishmael? So what's the reason of Rabi
Yishmael? דכתיב, D'chtiv, שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך. shofech dam ha'adam
ba'adam damo yishapech.
So
the פסוק pasuk is שופך דם האדם shofech dam ha'adam and then
the normal way to have read it was באדם דמו ישפך, ba'adam
damo yishapech, sorry. But
here Rabi Yishmael is doing something interesting, saying שופך דם האדם באדם.
shofech dam ha'adam ba'adam.
When is there a man in a man? איזהו אדם שבתוך אדם?
Eizehu adam she'betoch adam? When do you have a man in another
man, or a human in another human, let's talk about that. הוי
אומר זה עובר שבמעי אמו. Hevei omer zeh ubar she'bimei imo. So
the time you have a person in another person is in the
case of a fetus which is in its mother. And in that
case, Rabi Yishmael says that a person,
a non-Jew kills a fetus, then he should be tried even with
all these circumstances, even with all these limited things, such as just
one witness and one judge. It's considered murder as I believe he
goes by one witness and one judge. He's talking about the non-Jew,
right? Yeah, this is all regarding a non-Jew. A Jew would have
to have their own set of laws, right?
Did you guys talk about what Rabbi Linszer sort of his whole
setup of the בן
נח? ben Noach? The past few days have been spoken about it.
What do you mean by that?
I don't know, but yesterday they gave an interesting insight about this.
Like?
Well, this is what I was looking at from yesterday. So since
we're behind them, that's fine, but the issue of the ישראל שכתוב
בספר Yisrael she'katuv b'sefer or ישראל שכתוב בתורה, Yisrael she'katuv b'Torah, who
exactly do they mean by these Jews that they
think
they allowed themselves or they allowed themselves
to
be more lenient
towards?
Who is he referring to?
I don't know, but if it refers to whatever Christian slash early
Christian Romans who kind of are in sub-types, so we could at
least understand the mindset of whatever, we're in war with these people
and they're hurting us, therefore
we're allowed to get back at them. But if it means as
Rabbi Linszer just
translated as non-Jews, גוים, goyim, right? Like just generic, then it gets
very, very dangerous in our state. Yeah,
I
think it's problematic.
Not that the first is good, but at least you can understand
it. This just seems
worse.
I also think that one of the interesting things that's been coming
up in this עמוד amud
is sort of like, okay, I hear that there may be this
הלכה halacha with non-Jews with regards to what we think about them.
But I, there's this הלכה halacha system for בני נח. bnei Noach.
They have their own system, and we have our own system, although
we're in charge of both systems. The question is what happens when
they start interacting? So I don't know if that came up at
all, but what happens when a non-Jew kills a Jew? Right? Or
it just happens? Yeah, we did discuss it. Okay, great. So it's
going to come up again later. But yeah,
when the systems start interacting, then it's like, what? Does this other
system, is it not a, like it doesn't just become a caste
system that there's certain legal rules applied to one group but not
to another?
I'm not clear like when did they accept it? Like we barely
accepted our own system. When did they say that they are...
Is he saying this is a completely theoretical question?
Yeah, what's like whatever, me deciding someone else has these מצוות mitzvot
and this is what they have to do, and if not I'm
going to kill them? Like when was there a mutual thing that
said, yes, we're
citizens
of the same country and the same code?
Right. Today it would probably be the closest analog to like international
law. Okay. We'll leave it,
we'll leave it there. 57A. Okay.
Let's continue so we don't stay too far behind. So איזהו אדם
שבתוך אדם, Eizehu adam she'betoch adam, ורבנן. V'rabbanan.
So
the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who holds
that the, in the case of an עובר, ubar, this case of
a fetus, does not have the, that he wouldn't be killed for
it, why not? תנא דבי מנשה, Tanna d'vei Menashe, so he is
a תנא Tanna from דבי מנשה d'vei Menashe from a different school,
דאמר כל מיתה אמורה לבני נח אינו אלא חנק. d'amar kol mita
amura l'vnei Noach eino ela chenek. That he says that any death
that is prescribed to a בן נח, ben Noach, that's always going
to be done through strangulation. שדי ליה האי באדם אסיפא דקרא. Shadei
lei hai ba'adam asifa d'kra. דאמר de'amar כל מיתה אמורה לבני נח
אינה אלא חנק Chenek. *d'amar kol mitah amurah l'vnei Noach einah ella
chenek*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that any death that is prescribed
to בני נח Bnei Noach *Bnei Noach*, that's always going to be
done through strangulation. שדי ליה האי דאדם אסיפא דקרא *shadi lei hai
d'adam asseifa d'kra*. And so he uses, as opposed to being able
to say אדם Adam באדם *Adam b'Adam*, he uses באדם *b'Adam* as
connecting to the second half of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. וידרוש בהו
הני זימני אחרי הכי באדם דמו ישפך *v'idrosh behu hanei zimnei acharei
hachi b'Adam damo yishafech*. איזהו שפיכות דמים של אדם שהוא בגופו של
אדם? הוי אומר זה חנק Chenek *eizehu shefichut damim shel adam shehu
b'gufo shel adam? hevei omer zeh chenek*. So as opposed to seeing
the אדם באדם *Adam b'Adam* as a way of referring to the
death of the fetus, he uses באדם *b'Adam* as a way of
referring to the how the person is killed. And he says, what
is the case of having blood, the person being killed when the
blood remains inside? He says, well that kind of death is going
to be strangulation. Because when a person gets strangled, their blood remains
inside. There
is
no, as opposed to like stoning or using a sword or beheading
where blood is clearly being expelled from the body. מתיבי רב המנונא
*meitivei Rav Hamnuna*.
So רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* asks, אשה לא נפקדא *ishah
lo nifkada*, and why are women laid out of this? הכתיב *hachativ*,
but I have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, כי ידעתיו למען אשר יצוה
*ki yedativ l'maan asher yetzaveh*, but it is a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
open, it is a famous פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in these walls. The
רב *Rav* actually described this as sort of the,
one of the main, like a bridge or the main mission statement
for the Jewish people in Hashem's discussion with אברהם *Avraham*. He says
כי ידעתיו למען אשר יצוה את בניו ואת ביתו אחריו ושמרו דרך
ה' לעשות צדקה ומשפט *ki yedativ l'maan asher yetzaveh et banav v'et
beito acharav v'shamru derech Hashem laasot tzedakah u'mishpat*. So that he commanded
his sons and his household after him and they will guard the
way of Hashem to do צדקה ומשפט *tzedakah u'mishpat*. So רב המנונא
*Rav Hamnuna* seems to want to say בניו ואת ביתו *banav v'et
beito*. If בניו *banav* is his sons, who was ביתו *beito*? ביתו
*beito* must be the, must be the women. So presumably they should
be included in and here we have לעשות צדקה ומשפט *laasot tzedakah
u'mishpat*. And we know that אברהם *Avraham* is a בן נח Ben
Noach *Ben Noach*, so it sounds like the women are going to
be included in the משפט *mishpat*, in the judicial system. So רב
המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* sort of brings a, I do not want to
say feminist, but anachronistically brings in this sort of thing like hey,
this should include, this should include women as well.
Is
not there a difference though between defendant and the power structure within
the court system and the judge?
So this could mean yes, women are subject to the laws but
still not that they can be the witnesses and the judges.
I
would read this as being part of the מינוי דיינים dayanim *minui
dayanim*.
I think she, I think everyone agrees she is still subjective to
the laws.
I do not think anyone is challenging whether she is included in
the laws. This is about whether she could be a, a witness
or a judge. Because
נפקדא *nifkada*, what does
that word mean? Let us talk about that a little bit more
on that point. Yeah, נפקדא *nifkada*. ומשכחת לה בסיפא דבני
נח לא נפקדא אדינין *u'mashkachat lah b'seifa d'Bnei Noach lo nifkada a'dinin*.
She is not appointed or being a part of the דין *din*
himself.
I think it would be hard, it would be hard for me
to understand the situation in which women are not subjected to the
laws. I think we can all agree to that.
Okay, now do you have a, do you have a גמרא *Gemara*?
You have
it? Let us come back. Yes.
Okay. So, ומוסיף לה בר בירידא סוף *u'mosif lah bar bereida sof*.
Not only did he ask the question, he also gave the answer.
בניו לדינין ביתו לצדקה *banav l'dinin beito l'tzedakah*. So we had two,
we had two applications here. Sorry to interrupt. לעשות צדקה ומשפט *laasot
tzedakah u'mishpat*. So בניו *banav*, they are the ones to take care
of משפט *mishpat*, and ביתו *beito*, or ביתו *beito*
which is household, the women, they are in charge of צדקה *tzedakah*
regarding something like charity. אמר ליה רב אביא סבא לרב פפא *amar
lei Rav Avia Sava l'Rav Pappa*, אימא Eima בת נח Bat Noach,
בהריגה לא תהרג *eima bat Noach b'hareigah lo tehareg*. So now רב
אביא סבא *Rav Avia Sava* or רב פפא *Rav Pappa* is asking
his question. He says well maybe a woman should not be killed,
but from a different, from a different פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. מיד איש
ish. ולא מיד אשה *miyad ish v'lo miyad ishah*, right? The פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* back regarding נח *Noach* seems to be מיד איש ish?
*miyad ish*. So do not tell me that איש ish ואיש *ish
v'ish* excludes her regarding judgment, maybe it should also exclude regarding being
a victim. So אמר ליה הכי אמר רב יהודה amar lei hachi
amar Rav Yehuda שופך
דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך.
shofech dam
ha-adam ba-adam damo yishapech. Whoever does the killing, doesn't
matter if it's a man or a woman. So you look at
the next פסוק pasuk, שופך דם האדם, shofech dam ha-adam, anyone who
kills or spills the blood, that can refer to anybody. So אימא
בת נח שזנתה לא תבעי, ima Bat Noach she-zinta lo taba'i, maybe
we say that a בת נח, a female non-Jew who commits adultery,
she should be exempted. דכתיב על כן יעזוב איש
dich'tiv al
ken ya'azov ish ולא אשה. ve-lo ishah. It is the פסוק pasuk
back in בראשית, Bereishit, therefore a man shall leave his father and
his mother ודבק באשתו, ve-davak be-ishto, and this is only referring to
men. Women don't have this same commandment regarding marriage or that they
would be required to be married. So אמר ליה הכי אמר רב
יהודה והיו לבשר אחד. ve-hayu le-vasar echad. הדר ערבינהו קרא. hadar arebinhu
kra. Since the פסוק then goes back says והיו לבשר אחד, ve-hayu
le-vasar echad, they will be of one flesh, that sort of says
we're talking about both men and women. And once we see they're
talking about men and women in that case, we're going to like
retroactively look back and say that that's also referring to men and
women even though it only used the word איש. תנו
רבנן tanu rabbanan
איש מה תלמוד
לומר ish mah talmud lomar
איש איש ish ish לרבות את הכותים שמוזהרין על העריות כישראל. lerabbot
et ha-Kutim she-muzharin al ha-arayot k'Yisrael. So in the, in פרק perek
in ויקרא י"ח, Vayikra Yud-Chet, which is the section on all the
עריות, arayot, it has איש איש. ish ish. So what's the second
איש? That's to include even the כותים Kutim that they are, they
have the same עריות arayot as
ישראל. Yisrael. ומהכא נפקא? ולהלן נפקא? u-me-hacha nafka? u-le-halan nafka? You learned
from over there from לאמור leymor דגילוי עריות. de-gilluy arayot. That was
the גמרא a דף daf or two ago where they had the
word לאמור leymor and they used that to דרשן darshan that it
applies to non-Jews as well, rather than from the extra word איש
they use the, they do a דרשה drasha on the word לאמור.
leymor. דהכא בעריות דידהו והכא בעריות דידן.
de-hacha be-arayot dideyhu ve-hacha
be-arayot didan. No over there, over there, that's reference to their עריות.
arayot. And so the לאמור leymor means that non-Jews are commanded for
עריות arayot and for us for איש איש, ish ish, that means
regarding the Jewish עריות. arayot. דקתני סיפא הבא על עריות ישראל נידון
בדיני ישראל.
de-kateni seifa ha-ba al
arayot Yisrael nidon be-dinei Yisrael. Because we know from the סיפא seifa
over there they said oh that presumably there's two different sets of
עריות arayot laws, one for non-Jews and one for concept and one
for Jews. And if a non, if a non-Jew interacts with a
Jew or commits one of the עריות arayot with a Jew, then
we use the Jewish
system, they're judged by our rules. למאי הלכתא? le-mai hilchata? So how
does
this,
what is the נפקא מינא nafka mina here? What's the, what's the
implication of this? What is this, what is this distinction important? אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה לא נצרכה אלא לעד ודיין ולא
התראה.
amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha lo nitzrecha
ela le-ed ve-dayan ve-lo hasra. So he says oh what's the implication
that we know, so what we laid out at the beginning of
this עמוד. amud. Their system you only need one עד, ed, one
דיין, dayan, no התראה. hasra. And in our system we need two
עדים, edim, two, at least twenty-three דיינים to put to death, and
you would need התראה. hasra. They said אטו מיגרע גרע? atu migra
gara? Like that can't be, and it seems to be all backwards.
Any time if a non-Jew commits adultery, does some sort of זנות
znut or עריות arayot with a non-Jew it would be easier for
them to be put to death, but they do it with one
of our own then it would be harder to put them to
death? That would make our system, that would, that would seem like
worse for us. Presumably we want to be protected, it seems like
a lower standard than for the non-Jews. We wouldn't want that. אלא
אמר רבי יוחנן לא נצרכה אלא לנערה מאורסה.
ella amar Rabbi Yochanan lo nitzrecha ela
le-na'arah me-orasah. So he says no it's not about the system that
we utilize, rather אלא לא נצרכה אלא לנערה מאורסה.
ella lo nitzrecha ela le-na'arah
me-orasah. So they're going to come up with one particular case where
there's a distinction between their עריות arayot and our עריות. arayot. What's
that case? Case of נערה מאורסה. na'arah me-orasah. לדידהו לית להו דדיני
להו בדיני דידן אית להו.
le-dideyhu leit lehu de-dinei lehu be-dinei
didan it lehu. So right for a case of a נערה מאורסה
na'arah me-orasah for them that's not going to be considered עריות arayot
because the אירוסין eirusin process
only exists in Jewish law. The idea that we split the, we
split marriage into אירוסין eirusin and נישואין. nissu'in. So we have the
status of a betrothed woman but the non-Jews don't have that. So
in the case where a non-Jew
does some sort of עריות arayot with a נערה מאורסה, na'arah me-orasah,
that's going to be a case where we have to apply the
Jewish law rather than the non-Jewish law. As we're always going to
take the one עד, Ed, one דיין, Dayan, one התראה—or Hasra no
התראה—system Hasra for non-Jews. In the case of נערה מאורסה, Na'arah Meorasah,
that doesn't exist in their world at all. So that's where we
have to apply our
law. About אשת איש? Eshes Ish? בדינא דידהו דיינינן להו.
Bedina Did'hu
Dayninan Lehu. But for אשת איש, Eshes Ish, that is for just
a standard case of a married person, the case of adultery, they
have laws for that and therefore we can use their standard. והתניא,
Vehasanya, but we learned in a ברייתא, Braisa, בא על נערה מאורסה
נידון בסקילה, Ba Al Na'arah Meorasah Nidon Bisekila, על אשת איש נידון
בחנק,
Al Eshes Ish
Nidon Bichenek, ואי בדינא דידהו סיף הוא. Vee Bedina Did'hu Sayif Hu.
So now we ask the question, our understanding is in the case
a person has sex with a נערה המאורסה, Na'arah HaMeorasah, the betrothed
woman, so they're going to get סקילה, Sekila, and then אשת איש,
Eshes Ish, they're going to
get חנק. chenek. But if
we're dealing with their laws, he should have gotten סיף, Sayif, he
should have been beheaded. Right? The fact that סקילה Sekila sounds like
it's the Jewish... the סקילה Sekila and
חנק chenek make it
sound like we're totally in the context of the Jewish law, but
we should know for אשת איש Eshes Ish it should have been
סיף, Sayif, should have been beheaded. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar
Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak, מאי אשת איש? Mai Eshes Ish? So what
does it mean אשת איש? Eshes Ish? So we're going to have
another little nuance here in order to get out of this seeming
contradiction, because presumably we had said before that נערה מאורסה Na'arah Meorasah
was the only case that distinguished that would fall out on this
line between their law and our law. But in the case of
אשת איש Eshes Ish also is being judged by our system rather
than their system. מאי אשת איש? Mai Eshes Ish? דקתני כגון שנכנסה
לחופה ולא נבעלה, Dekasani Kegon Shenichnesah LeChuppah Velo Nivalah, דלדידהו לית להו,
Delididu Leis Lehu, דאני להו בדינא דידן. Deani Lo Bedina Didan. So
we had this other wrinkle that there's this other time period, which
is post-חופה Chuppah but before any sort of ביאה. Biah. And for
us, that would already be considered נישואין, Nissuin, but for non-Jews, they
would need the sex in order for it to be considered an
אשת איש. Eshes Ish. After the חופה. Chuppah. Yeah. Or meaning, I
think or the assumption here is that since they're not having חופות,
Chuppahs, then the only thing that indicates the finalization of whatever the
marriage is, the partnership, would be the sex. So they must not
be imagining some ceremony, otherwise it would just still be an engaged
wife, right? Right, it sounds like they don't think... we presume that
the בני נח Bnei Noach aren't having any sort of אירוסין Eirusin
or נישואין. Nissuin. Oh wait, so we're talking about a Jewish woman
here, right? Correct, rather a Jewish woman because she's had a חופה
Chuppah from our perspective, yeah. No, okay. So דתניא הכי נמי, Detanya
Hachi Nami, ובעולת בעל יש להם. Uveulas Baal Yesh Lahem. They do
have בעולת בעל Beulas Baal where they have sex, נכנסה לחופה ולא
נבעלה אין להם. Nichnesah LeChuppah Velo Nivalah Ein Lahem. They don't have
any concept of having the ceremony, marriage ceremony, without any sort of
sexual consummation to way follow up that. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן: Tanya
Kevasei DeRabbi Yochanan: a ברייתא Braisa like Rabbi Yochanan. כל ערווה שבית
דין של ישראל ממיתין עליה בן נח מוזהר עליה. Kol Ervah SheBeis
Din Shel Yisrael Mamisin Aleha Ben Noach Muzhar Aleha. אין בית דין
של ישראל ממיתין עליה אין בן נח מוזהר עליה. Ein Beis Din
Shel Yisrael Mamisin Aleha Ein Ben Noach Muzhar Aleha. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים הרבה עריות יש שאין בית דין של
ישראל ממיתין עליהן ובן נח מוזהר עליהן. VeChachamim Omrim Harbeh Arayos Yesh
SheEin Beis Din Shel Yisrael Mamisin Alehen Uven Noach Muzhar Alehen. And
here we have this ברייתא Braisa that says that any ערווה Ervah
that בית דין Beis Din can kill over, בן נח Ben Noach
is also considered like warned on and that falls under
their
system. But if בית דין, Beis Din, Jewish בית דין Beis Din
cannot kill, then the בן נח ben Noach is not obligated himself.
So that's Rabbi Meir. And says וחכמים אומרים, VeChachamim Omrim, what are
you talking about? There's lots of עריות Arayos that even though the
Jewish law wouldn't require a death, nonetheless non... the בני נח bnei
Noach. would
still
be obligated it. בא על ערוות ישראל נידון בדיני ישראל,
Ba Al Ervas Yisrael Nidon
Bedinei Yisrael,
בא על ערוות בן נח נידון בדיני בן נח. Ba Al Ervas
Ben Noach Nidon Bedinei Ben Noach. ואנו
אין לנו אלא נערה מאורסה בלבד. V'anu Ein Lanu Ela Na'arah Meorasah
Bilvad. ונוסיף נמי נכנסה לחופה ולא נבעלה. Venossif Nami Nichnesah LeChuppah Velo
Nivalah.
So we have this ברייתא Braisa which stuff seems to point to
the same exact exceptions that we just mentioned: נערה מאורסה Na'arah Meorasah
and the situation of post-חופה Chuppah pre-sex. האי תנא תנא דבי מנשה.
Hai tanna, tanna d'bei Menashe.
So this תנא tanna is תנא דבי מנשה tanna d'bei Menashe and
הוא דאמר hu de'amar כל מיתה האמורה בבני נח אינה אלא חנק.
kol mitah ha'amurah b'venei Noach einah ela chenek. So this all points
to תנא דבי מנשה tanna d'bei Menashe who said that all of
any
death for a non-Jew is case of חנק. אידי ואידי חנק הוא.
Idi v'idi chenek hu. And then all what
what were our laws would be equal in this regard that חנק
in this in this situation. וסבר רבי מאיר כל ערווה שבית דין
של ישראל ממיתין עליה בן נח מוזהר עליה. V'savar Rabbi Meir kol
ervah she'beit din shel Yisrael memitin aleha ben Noach muzhar aleha. Does
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir really hold that any situation any case that
a בית דין beit din would kill over, a בן נח Ben
Noach is warned about? והתניא, Vehatanya, we have a ברייתא. braita. גר
שהייתה הורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה יש לו
שאר האם ואין
לו שאר האב.
Ger shehayeta horato shelo b'kedushah v'lidato b'kedushah yesh lo
she'er ha'em v'ein
lo she'er ha'av.
So here's the case is that a baby that was conceived when
his mother was not Jewish and then his mother converted while
she
was pregnant with him, so that's הורתו שלא בקדושה, horato shelo b'kedushah,
he was conceived as a non-Jew and then he was born as
a Jew. So he is going to have relatives through his mother
and not have relatives through his father. So just to clarify what's
going on here, we know that a גר ger when they convert
technically they're not related to anybody else, any of their previous relationships.
And therefore, if somebody who they were related to also converted, they
typically they wouldn't be allowed to get married to because of the
biological connection. That's not going to be true if they both convert.
But it's the mom who converted.
The mom's converted, yeah.
Why does it not apply to the father?
So in this case we say that he is going to be,
he is not going to be allowed to have to marry anybody
related through his mother, because he is born as a Jew and
she converted while he was in her.
So he's related to the mother, meaning other children?
Yeah, previous, let's say she had a previous daughter or something like
that. So theoretically let's say, what? Yeah, from the
mother.
Have
you watched Game of Thrones? It sounds like that.
I thought he's not related because they both convert. That's the point.
But the point is that since he was born as a Jew,
he is going to have the same issues of certain relationships. But
for his father, whose the only interaction with his father's DNA was
pre-Jewishness,
then any relationship to his father, let's say a half-sister through his
father, he theoretically would be allowed to marry. Or his father's sister
or something like that. Can you repeat that? So כיצד, keitzad, נשא
אחותו מן האם, nasa achoto min ha'em, יוציא, yotzi, מן האב, יקיים.
min ha'av yekayem,
So if he marries a half-sister
from his mother, a previous wouldn't, it can't be a later daughter,
it has to be a daughter she had
previously, that יוציא, yotzi, we have to we say that marriage can't
can't go on, he has to dissolve that, מן האב min ha'av,
יקיים, yekayem. but if he tries to marry a half-sister of his
father, we say that that marriage exists. Presumably
she the half-sister from the father also converted. אחות
האב מן האם
יוציא
מן האב יקיים.
Achot ha'av min ha'em yotzi min
ha'av
yekayem. So this is now
sisters
of his father
that
are maternal. Or paternal.
No.
So this is a case of, sorry this gets a little complicated.
אחות אביו מן האמו. Achot aviv min ha'imo.
How
do you translate יוציא? yotzi?
That word dissolving the marriage, so we're no we don't allow that
marriage to exist.
People can't marry. Correct. And יקיים yekayem is they can marry.
You got it. So this is his father's sister. Sorry, his father's
sister who's a half-sister who's a maternal half-sister. So this is his
aunt. So his father's mother had two children, each from a different
husband. This person's grandmother was married twice. His paternal grandmother was married
twice. She has her son who's this גר's ger father, and she
also has another daughter. And that's the אחות האב מן האם. achot
ha'av min ha'em. Father's half-sister from his mother. From grandmother.
מן האם min ha'em is grandmother.
Yeah, the father's
mom. יוציא. yotzi. יוציא, Yotzi, don't like that one. מן האם יתקיים.
Min ha'em yitkayem. But if it's a
father,
if it's a shared sibling from the grandfather side, then
yeah, because so then the maternal line here becomes the important part,
that the עריות arayot connected to the women is harsher than עריות
arayot connected to the men.
We talked about this before when I mentioned it in
different names for uncle on the mother's side and uncle on the
father's side, it doesn't work the same way, whatever, so there
is
a distinction between how close you are to your mother's family and
how close you are to your father's family.
And the fact that you're closer to one side,
I'm not saying it translates here, but
I think assuming that there's something uncomfortable or something taboo about
these
relationships presumes a deeper connection
on
the mother's
side.
We don't make these distinctions.
Yeah, I think a classic thing would be a person... we don't
make a distinction between the father's side or the mother's side, but
we do have a distinction that a person can marry their aunt
but an uncle can't marry his niece.
I don't know if it's the same thing.
What's the reason for that distinction? Like by הלכה? halacha?
They say
הלכה halacha that a person can marry
their...
no other way around, sorry. Other way around. Abraham marries Sarah who's
Nahor's daughter,
but you wouldn't be allowed to marry your aunt.
Okay let's keep
going. אחות האם מן האם יוציא, Achot ha'em min ha'em yotzi, אחות
האם מן האב,
Achot ha'em
min ha'av, רבי מאיר אומר יוציא וחכמים אומרים יתקיים.
Rabbi Meir omer yotzi vechachamim
omrim yitkayem. So now this is the
opposite case, this is where we're talking about the mother's sisters and
the question is: are those sisters half-sisters from the grandfather, half-sisters from
the grandmother? And if it's the mother's sister from the grandmother, everybody
agrees that that would be a no-go. But if it's the mother's
sister from the grandfather, then it's a question. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi
Meir omer, not good, חכמים chachamim say it's okay. רבי מאיר אומר
כל ערווה שהיא משום שאר אם יוציא משום שאר אב יתקיים.
Rabbi Meir omer kol ervah she'hi
mishum she'er em yotzi mishum she'er av yitkayem. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says it's all about if there's a maternal
connection
then
we're done for, if it's just the whole connection is paternal then
it's not going to be a problem. ומותר באשת אחיו ובאשת אחי
אביו. Umutar be'eshet achiv uve'eshet achi aviv.
And he can marry the wife of his brother and the wife
of his uncle. ושאר
כל העריות מותרות לו.
Veshe'er kol ha'arayot mutarot
lo. And all the other עריות arayot are permitted to him. So
this we're talking still talking about the גר. Ger. So the גר
Ger can marry the wife of his brother who,
meaning his brother, his non-Jewish brother, or sorry, his brother who was
converted separately. And he can marry the wife of his uncle.
Okay? And any other עריות arayot would be permitted to him. לאתויי
אשת אביו. Le'atuyei eshet aviv. And this is to include
his father's wife.
So when we say ושאר כל העריות, veshe'er kol ha'arayot, that means
his father, okay he had a separate wife and then his father
dies, this גר Ger would be allowed to marry his father's wife.
I guess they're in like a small town, there's no one else.
Just
go to the next village. Okay so, נשא אישה ובתה כונס אחת
ומוציא אחת. Nasa isha uvita kones achat umotzi achat. If he marries
a woman and her daughter, so he should have sex with one
and the other
one he should cancel that relationship, ולכתחילה לא יכנוס, velechatchila lo yichnos,
but לכתחילה lechatchila he shouldn't do this, should never be in this
situation. מתה אשתו
מותר בחמותו.
Meta ishto
mutar bechamoto. If his wife dies,
he's permitted to his mother-in-law. ויש
אומרים אסור בחמותו. Veyesh omrim asur bechamoto. And there are those who
say that he's אסור asur to his mother-in-law. אמר
רב יהודה לא קשיא. Amar Rav Yehuda lo kashya. So to be
clear what the question is, for
before רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir had said all ערוה erva that a
בת ישראל bas Yisrael will kill over, a בן נח Ben Noach
is warned about. And yet here,
hold
on. So the question is, what's the question? Who can get it?
This is a test for everyone. The question is here, the implication
seems to be that there are ערוות ervas that he needs to
avoid
that a Jew wouldn't be killed over. I think that's the question.
So
I think these cases of
in the רש"י Rashi חסר המפרש chasar hameforesh דמאי דקתני d'mai d'katani
מיד מותר באשת אביו miyad mutar b'eishes aviv that you would be
permitted in his father's wife אף על פי שבית דין של ישראל
נהרגים עליה.
af al pi shebeis din
shel Yisrael neheragim aleha. וכן בחמותו, V'chein b'chamato, and also with his
mother-in-law. וקתני אסור באחותו ובאחות אביו ובאחות אמו U'katani asur b'achoso u'v'achose
aviv u'v'achose imo אף על פי שאין בית דין של ישראל נהרגים
עליהן. af al pi she'ein beis din shel Yisrael neheragim aleihen. So
we have this situation where the משנה mishna seems to imply that
it would be אסור asur for a בן נח to marry his
sister or the sisters of his father or his mother. And yet
here I guess we seem to have a case of the גר
ger where he's permitted to marry the sisters of his father or
his mother, assuming they fall into the categories. And therefore this seems
to be a question on רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So that was
the גמרא'ס Gemara's point. So
we say, don't worry, הא רבי מאיר אליבא דרבי אלעזר והא רבי
מאיר אליבא דרבי עקיבא. ha Rabbi Meir aliba d'Rabbi Elazar v'ha Rabbi
Meir aliba d'Rabbi Akiva. No, Rabbi Eleazar and Rabbi Akiva have different
interpretations of Rabbi Meir. תניא אידך ברייתא, Tanya idach braisa, על כן
יעזב איש את אביו ואת אמו.
al kein ya'azov
ish es aviv v'es imo. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אביו
אחות אביו, aviv achose aviv, אמו אחות
אמו. imo achose imo. So
in
terms of a non-Jew
who isn't allowed to marry his aunt, we consider עריות. arayos.
So we learn this from the פסוקים pesukim of על כן יעזב
איש את אביו ואת אמו. al kein ya'azov ish es aviv v'es
imo. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says אביו aviv refers to his paternal
aunt, אמו imo refers to his maternal aunt. So אביו aviv refers
to his paternal aunt, אמו imo refers to his maternal aunt. So
this is not just like some nice fluffy פסוק that we like
to say at weddings, but that there's actually implications here in terms
of the laws of בני נח. bnei Noach And so רבי עקיבא
אומר, אביו אשת אביו, Rabbi Akiva omer aviv eshet aviv. אמו אמו
ממש. imo imo mamash. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, what are
you talking about? אביו aviv means it's an ערוה erva for him
to sleep with his father's wife, I guess a step-wife, and אמו
imo refers to don't have sex with one's mother. ודבק, V'davak, ולא
בזכר. v'lo b'zachar. And the fact that it says ודבק v'davak implies
that a man shouldn't have sex with another man. באשתו, B'ishto, ולא
באשת חבירו. v'lo b'eishes chaveiro. So ודבק באשתו, v'davak b'ishto, they shall
become as his own wife and not with his friend's wife. So
this is the issue of אשת איש. eishes ish. והיו לבשר אחד,
V'hayu l'vasar echad, and they will be of one flesh. במי שנעשים
בשר אחד, B'mi she'na'asim basar echad, so this would only refer
to people who'll be able to have one flesh with, which they
interpret as having children with. So since you can only have children
with humans, this is also a warning against bestiality. יצאו בהמה וחיה
שאין נעשים בשר אחד. Yatzu behema v'chaya she'ein na'asim basar echad. Great.
So אמר מר, Amar mar,
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אביו אחות אביו. aviv achose aviv.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had interpreted אביו aviv as אחות אביו, achose
aviv, right, על כן יעזב אביו ואמו. al kein ya'azov aviv v'imo.
So he said אביו aviv refers to his paternal aunt. אמו... Imo...
אביו ממש, aviv mamash, I would say why doesn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer say that אביו aviv is literally just don't have relations with
your father. So we say,
היינו ודבק ולא בזכר, hainu v'davak v'lo b'zachar, we already had the
later law of ודבק v'davak and not a זכר, zachar, so if
you can't have sex with any man, then that obviously is going
to include your father as well.
אימא אשת אביו, Eima eshes aviv, so I would say why doesn't
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer hold like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that אביו
aviv should mean אשת אביו eshes aviv rather than אחות אביו. achose
aviv. So we say, היינו באשתו ולא באשת חבירו, hainu b'ishto v'lo
b'eishes chaveiro, no, that is also included from the later law, the
later law says that any married woman, so that would also have
to include his father's second wife or previous wife.
death and not just I guess post-divorce, as
in meaning if she was his father's wife but she's no longer
his wife? Right.
אימא Eima so then it would be permitted.
Right, so then we need אביו, Aviv, right?
Even if it
does
come out that you're not allowed to sleep with your father's wife
while he's alive, but it doesn't say that... Right. Right.
But so I think essentially what they're trying to figure out is
how to interpret
אביו Aviv
to saying אימא maybe that's what you're saying also. אימא לאחר מיתה
Eima le-achar mita that I would say אביו Aviv what does that
mean? It means the wife of a father even after death that
would be prohibited.
So they know, do we need to use the פסוק for that?
Why not?
דמיא ליה לאימו Damya lei le-imo מה אימו דלאו אישות ma imo
delav ishut אף אשת
אביו דלאו אישות.
af eshet aviv
delav ishut.
Just like his mother becomes אסור asur to him and has nothing
to do with marriage but rather because it's his mother, so too
for אביו Aviv we would say that any of the father's spouses
we would say that's prohibited to him not because she's an אשת
איש Eshet Ish
which in the case of אשת איש Eshet Ish we would typically
say a person is permitted post-death, but she's prohibited because she's connected
to his father. So that has to do with his
son-to-parent relationship rather than a marriage.
OK, cool. ואימא אמו ממש
Ve-eima imo mamash
היינו באשתו ולא באשת חבירו. hainu be-ishto ve-lo be-eshet chaveiro. OK, so
now we're going back to challenge Rabbi Akiva who had interpreted אמו
Imo as אמו ממש. Imo mamash. Rabbi Akiva said what does it
mean, ערות אביו וערות אמו, ervat aviv ve-ervat imo, and the fact
that it lists his mother means don't have sex with her, literally.
So now we're questioning Rabbi Akiva's interpretation to say, I don't
understand, היינו באשתו ולא באשת חבירו. hainu be-ishto ve-lo be-eshet chaveiro. His
mother should be excluded by the fact that it's his father's wife,
so אשת חבירו. eshet chaveiro. ואימא לאחר מיתה. Ve-eima le-achar mita.
And I would say for the same question again, even at death,
even post-death, that it should and it should be permitted. Right. So
they know דמיא לאביו damya le-aviv מה אביו דלאו ממש ma aviv
delav mamash אף אמו דלאו ממש. af imo delav mamash. No, just
like the father isn't interpreted literally to refer to the father, rather
to refer to the aunt or to father's wife, so too אמו
Imo shouldn't be interpreted literally.
רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer, אביו אשת אביו. aviv eshes aviv,
Rabbi Akiva said that his father refers to his wife, his father's
wife. ואימא אביו ממש. Ve-eima aviv mamash. And I'll say why don't
we say it refers to
אביו Aviv himself? היינו בדבר שלאו בזכר. Hainu be-davar she-lav be-zachar. So
no, that was already taught from the ואת זכר. ve-et zachar. אי
הכי אשת אביו נמי
Ei hachi eshet
aviv nami היינו באשתו ולא באשת חבירו. hainu be-ishto ve-lo be-eshet chaveiro.
See, I don't understand, if that's true then אשת אביו eshet aviv
his father's wife... yeah, just to be clear what we're doing, we're
looking at each of these and challenging them all from the same...
everyone's getting the same treatment of why this is not included in
another law, so trying to figure out why
each of these specific situations needs to be learned from these words.
לאחר מיתה. Le-achar mita.
So maybe it should be for after death.
אמו
אמו ממש Imo imo mamash היינו באשתו
ולא...
hainu be-ishto
ve-lo... oh, so he actually answered לאחר מיתה le-achar mita it would
be permitted
exactly. So in the case of his father's wife according to Rabbi
Akiva
once his father died he would be allowed to marry his father's
wife.
Oh, weren't we just saying why we need a specific, why we
need
אביו Aviv and אמו? Imo?
Sorry, yes, totally right. Let's just reverse roles. That works. אמו אמו
ממש Imo imo mamash
היינו באשתו ולא באשת חבירו. hainu be-ishto ve-lo be-eshet chaveiro. That's the
באשתו be-ishto and אשת חבירו. eshet chaveiro. אמו מאנוסתו. Imo me-anusato. So
no, this refers to his mother who wasn't his father's wife. So
let's say he's the product of his father and a woman who
his father raped.
This is very Game of Thrones. Yeah. So this is, he's the
son
of his father and the woman whom his father raped, and therefore
אשת אביו Eshet Aviv
is
not going to be his
mother and his mother is never going to be included in the
category of
אשת... Eshet... So מאי קא מיפלגי? Mai kamifligi? So what are Rabbi
Eliezer and Rabbi Akiva arguing about? Just in case it wasn't obvious
from
the last page. So רבי
אליעזר
סבר Rabbi Eliezer savar אביו דומיא דאמו aviv dumya de-imo ואמו דומיא
דאביו ve-imo dumya de-aviv ולא משכחת לה velo mishkachat lah אלא באחותו.
ela beachoto. רבי עקיבא אמר איצטריך אשת אביו למיפתי ערבת אביו לאפוקי
אחות אביו שהרי אחות אביו לאו אשת אביו היא.
Rabbi Akiva amar itzterich eshet aviv lemaptei ervat aviv
la’apoki achot aviv sheharei achot aviv lav eshet aviv hi. Okay. So
Rabbi Eliezer holds that where are he wants to make fathers and
אביו aviv and אמו imo as equivalent categories. And therefore he says
for both of them they're referring to sibs their siblings their sisters.
But for Rabbi Akiva he doesn't
he doesn't create that same
categorical cohesiveness. Rather he says that for אשת אביו eshet aviv that's
going to be considered ערבת אביו ervat aviv but אחות אביו achot
aviv is just considered שאר אביו. she’er aviv. So in ויקרא Vayikra
we have this distinction between ערבה erva that is
has to do with the person who someone had sex with as
opposed to שאר she’er which has to do with somebody's relatives and
that's what's inappropriate about it. Then Rabbi Akiva said that for אשת
אביו eshet aviv that's considered ערבת אביו ervat aviv and that's going
to exclude his father's sisters who are considered שאר אביו she’er aviv
but they are not considered ערבת אביו. ervat aviv. תא
שמע.
Ta
shema. So come and hear ויקח עמרם את יוכבד דודתו. vayikach Amram
et Yocheved dodato.
מה לאו דודתו מן האם? ma lav dodato min ha’em? Is it
not his aunt from his mother?
And this by the way does not actually mean aunt from his
mother this means
father's
sister.
That's weird.
Because Yocheved comes from the tribe of Levi also, right? Right. Yocheved
is Levi's daughter and Amram is Levi's grandson through Kehat.
So that would not be אחות מן האם achot min ha’em that
would be I guess presumably אחות מן האב ומן
האם, achot min ha’av u-min ha’em, right? She's Levi's
daughter. Yeah. Not really. But I think that's the Gemara's point as
well. So it says מה לאו
דודתו מן האם
ma lav dodato
min ha’em
is it not his aunt through his mother? לא דודתו מן האב.
lo dodato min ha’av.
This is his father's sister. That seems pretty obvious, no?
So maybe it's like partly rhetorical. ויקח עמרם יוכבד דודתו. vayikach Amram
Yocheved dodato. מה לאו דודתו מן האם? ma lav dodato min ha’em?
לא דודתו מן האב. lo dodato min ha’av. So
therefore the implication here is that a person can marry their aunt.
This was before the Torah. תא שמע. Ta shema. וגם אמנה אחותי
בת אבי היא אך לא בת אמי.
vegam amnah achoti bat avi
hi ach lo bat imi.
So this is in Abraham's in Abraham one of Abraham's stories he
says she's my sister, sorry referring to Sarah as referring to Sarah
he says it's my sister the daughter of my
father. The implication is not the daughter of my mother. מכלל דבת
האם אסורה miklal debat ha'em asura and that implies that even for
בני נח at that time it was a daughter it was a
half-sister through the mother that would be problematic. Or sorry his Jewish
sister I guess. וסברא אחותו הוי בת אחיו הוי.
vesivra achoto havi
bat achiv havi. And we explain that אחותו achoto really means the
daughter of his brother. וכיון דאחיו הוא vekeivan de-achiv hu לא שנא
מן האב ולא שנא מן האם. lo shna min ha’av velo shna
min ha’em. And if we're doing the niece logic then it doesn't
matter whether it actually comes from a father's side or the mother's
side. The point is a niece would be permitted. שרה בת הרן.
Sarah bat Haran. אלא הכי קאמר ליה ela hachi ka’amar leh קורבה
דאחות אית לי בהדה מן האבא ולא מן האימא.
kurba de-achot it li bahadah
min ha’abba velo min ha’imma.
Oh, my relationship to this person is connected through the father and
not through the mother but not that she's literally.
A niece of a paternal first cousin. And
do one more minute? תא שמע Ta shema דאמר לא נשא
אדם את בתו.
lo nasa adam
et bito. Today, why didn't אדם marry his daughter? They
say, oh, in order so that קין Kayin would marry his sister,
שנאמר shenemar כי אמרתי עולם חסד יבנה.
ki amarti olam
chesed yibaneh. The said, "world of kindness will be built." הא לאו
הכי, ha lav hachi,
if we didn't have this פסוק that had said that קין Kayin
should be marrying his
sister, אסיר, assir, I would have said that it's אסור assur to
marry your
sister. דכיון דאישתרי
אישתרי, dekeivan deishtarei ishtarei, then we say we're taught back, no, it's
not the פסוק, once it's permitted, it's permitted. So once we have
this פסוק that said that he was allowed to marry his
sister, then it's going to be permitted.
Okay.
You want to talk?